<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The spirit of God in man, making manifest the hidden things of darkness to man. Being divine teachings, whereby the Lord alone is exalted, and the pride of fleshly glory discovered, / by the shining light of Christ in and through Richard Russel.</title>
            <author>Russel, Richard, theological writer.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1654</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 49 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 21 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A92133</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing R2347</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E1488_3</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R208500</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99867447</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99867447</idno>
            <idno type="VID">170026</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A92133)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 170026)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 191:E1488[3])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The spirit of God in man, making manifest the hidden things of darkness to man. Being divine teachings, whereby the Lord alone is exalted, and the pride of fleshly glory discovered, / by the shining light of Christ in and through Richard Russel.</title>
                  <author>Russel, Richard, theological writer.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[4], 36 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by T. Lock, living in Seacole-Lane neer the sign of the George.,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London, :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1654.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Annotation on Thomason copy: "April. 13.".</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Spiritual life --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Christian life --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-03</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-03</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-05</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-05</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:170026:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>THE SPIRIT OF GOD in MAN, Making manifeſt the hidden things of <hi>DARKNESS</hi> to <hi>MAN.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Being divine Teachings, whereby the Lord alone is exalted, and the pride of fleſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly glory diſcovered, by the ſhining light of Chriſt in and through <hi>RICHARD R<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>SSEL.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>1 Joh. 1.3.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <p>That which we have ſeen and heard declare we unto you, that ye alſo may have fellowſhip with us; and truly our fel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowſhip is with the Father and the Son Ieſus Chriſt.</p>
            </q>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Iſai. 60.1:</hi>
               </bibl>
               <p>Ariſe and ſhine, for thy light is come, and the glory of the Lord is riſen. Blow ye the Trumpet in <hi>Sion,</hi> and ſound an alarms in my holy Moutain; let all the Inhabitants of the Land tremble, for the day of the Lord cometh, for it is nigh at hand.</p>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed by <hi>T. Lock,</hi> living in <hi>Seacole-Lane</hi> neer the Sign of the <hi>George.</hi> 1654.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:170026:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:170026:2"/>
            <head>The Epiſtle to the READER.</head>
            <p>
               <hi>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">B</seg>Eloved Brethren;</hi> Spiritu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al things are given by Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine Inſpiration, not by the wil of Man, but by the wil of God, who manifeſts him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, when he pleaſeth, and to whom he pleaſeth: And know this that Gods works are not like mans works, he doth not always take the wiſe of this world, and learned and rich of this world, to manifeſt himſelf in and through, but be chooſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth the deſpiſed, and the poor and weak of this world, who are of a ſincere minde zealous for God, and God is pleaſed to fill them with the good things of himſelf, when as the other ſeek him in darkneſs, in the wiſdom of man, and by the Law, as did <hi>Iſrael</hi> of old, who ſought ear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſtly, but attained not to the true Viſion and Kingdom of righteouſneſs, but went empty a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way; therefore quench not the ſmoaking flax,
<pb facs="tcp:170026:3"/>but rather wait until it be ſet on flame, that it may kindle your ſpark, ſo that there may bee light in your houſe, for there is a wonderful time coming; but becauſe it beginneth in the night, there are many that ſhal not ſee it by rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of their ſleep and great darkneſs; yet the Son wil ſhine to the Children at midnight; happy are they whoſe eys are open to ſee the Son of GOD when he cometh in the clouds, then every one that hath a ſingle eye ſhal ſee the pleaſant ſhowers fall upon the tender plants, that they may alſo have vertue in them to abide the heat of the day, when the Son ſhal ſhine forth in its beauty to ſcorch the glory of all fleſh; therefore let every one that glorieth, glory onely in the Lord, for he that truly knows the Lord will do ſo, for the knowledge of the Lord teacheth us wiſdom, and ſo ſaith the Prophet <hi>Iſaiah, The Lord is my God therefore wil I praiſe him;</hi> for he knew God by his ſpirit, which did ſet forth his praiſe in him: therefore as thou rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſt, herein conſider, whether thou haſt the ſpirit of underſtanding, without which thou canſt not underſtand aright the things that be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>long unto thy peace. So I commit thee unto the Lord, who is able to guide thee unto the peace that paſſeth all underſtanding.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:170026:3"/>
            <head>THE SPIRIT OF GOD in MAN.</head>
            <div n="1" type="letter">
               <head>Epiſtle <hi>I.</hi> Concerning what Man was, and by Creation is, and how he fel; and alſo a word of the Divine Myſterie.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">G</seg>OD which was, is, and for ever ſhal be, a be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in himſelf, hath been pleaſed to declare the ſame in Creation, of which Creation man is a chief part; but be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the Creation there was nothing but God, no appearances were brought forth out of the one, onely infinite, and entire
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:170026:4"/>being, who knows how harmoniously and ſweetly with an entire love—and oneneſs we tumbled together with, in the womb of Eternity, when all things were in union with their Original Centre.</p>
               <p>Now when God was to create the world, and all things therein, he had no other materials (or matter) to make it of, but his own being; therefore God is the Eſſence of all Eſſences, for all is generated or born, created and proceeded from him, and all things take their firſt beginning in God, as the Scripture witneſſeth, ſaying, <hi>Through him, and in him are all things, and all things were created by him and for him, and by him all things conſiſt.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Conſider, That God is a Spirit that is in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>comprehenſible, and was before appearan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces were brought forth, by or in his eſſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tial Word, and hath neither beginning nor end, and his greatneſs and depth is all.</p>
               <p>The whole Creation is but his unfolding of himſelf in his varieties, and his cloath<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing himſelf in the creature in their created eſtate; ſo that ſince this great fabrick of heaven and earth hath bin made to appear, God hath ever been hiding himſelf, hiding himſelf in his life, being motions and ope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rations, ſo that no eye can ſee him, or know
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:170026:4"/>what he does, or what he means, but that eye which is with him where he is.</p>
               <p>This conſider, That every ſpirit ſeeth no further then into its Mother (or Nature) out of which it hath its Original, and wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in it ſtandeth; for it is impoſſible for any ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit, below the ſpirit of God, in its own natural power, to look into another princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, and behold it, except it be regenerated therein, or brought forth anew.</p>
               <p>Heaven and Earth at their firſt coming forth were but a vail, behinde which God intended to hide himſelf, and did hide him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, even from <hi>Adam,</hi> in his higheſt and pureſt eſtate; God indeed ſhowed himſelf to <hi>Adam,</hi> as he appeared in the creature, as he ſhined through the vail, but hid him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf as he was in himſelf, ſo that <hi>Adam</hi> could in no wiſe reach to the true viſion, but only to ſuch an appearance as God pleaſed to dart forth of himſelf through the vail.</p>
               <p>Now confider, when the breath of Liſe was breathed into man, (or elementary birth) it was out of Gods firſt principle, then Man was a living ſoul in the heavenly Paradiſe, wherein there was a ſtate of In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nocency, being the morning time of man, wherein was planted paradiſical fruit, which the garden <hi>[Man]</hi> ſhould bring forth, for
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:170026:5"/>God did make him a garden for his own delight to walk in, and that the creature ſhould delight in him, and to acknowledge God to be his Maker, and his all, his life and only being, to whoſe command he was to ſubject himſelf, in all obedience, meek<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, thankfulneſs, love, humility, and mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy, and ſo repreſent the glory of the Lord, and to be like him; if theſe things be in you, and abound, you ſhal not be unfruit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful, therefore let theſe things be applied to every one of our hearts in particular, theſe propheſying times.</p>
               <p>Again, obſerve this, that God foreknew that all created things are changeable, therefore God made a Law to man, for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bidding him of eating of the Tree of Knowledge of good and evil, which is in the midſt of the garden; <hi>for in the day thou eateſt thereof thou ſhalt ſurely dye; and this is the Law and Covenant that I have made between me and thee, that haſt a being in creation by me.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>This conſider, that man was made upright, but he being let ſtand did putrifie, — and ſo ſought out many inventions, <hi>Eecleſ.</hi> 7.29. ſo that there aſpited up in the midſt of the garden (the heart of man) pride and covetouſneſs, being not contnted with
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:170026:5"/>that eſtate that God had put him in by Creation, but did covet another eſtate, to exalt it ſelf, to be more knowing than God had made him; which ſelf-aſpiring the creature delighted in, and ſo eating or ſatiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fying himſelf in his own fruit, broke the Law and Covenant, and died, according to the words of his Maker, and ſo fell from a pure eſtate to be rebellious, and to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>light in his own ways, ſo that the root of mans fall, as he is a creature, ſprung in his heart, there lies the myſtery of iniquity; therefore conſider what is the forbidden fruit, which him that eateth thereof doth advance himſelf, and denies God, which is the creatures death, loſs and ſhame, and ever ſince the fall of man, this ſelfiſh aſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring ſpirit of pride leads the humane nature to diſobey God, and leads every man and woman captive at his will, and inslaves them in the priſon of bondage and darkneſs, to walk in ways directly contrary to the God of Truth and Light, and yet many times perſwades them that they do God good ſervice: let a man read, hear, ſtudy, preach, pray, and perform actions of juſtice, yet if God be not merciful to the man, this pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er of darkneſs will deceive him, making him conceit or think he pleaſeth God,
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:170026:6"/>when the truth is, he ſerves but himſelf all that time, if the Spirit of God be not their counſellor and ſupport, it is ſo ful of ſecret ſtrong deluſions, therefore this is cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led the crooked Serpent, becauſe it winds it ſelf into every creature, and into every faculty, and twiſts it ſelf about the Tree, <hi>(Mankind)</hi> ſo that the humane nature is defiled, and is a ſeat wherein the Beaſt and falſe Prophet ſitteth, and therein predomi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate, whereby Satans Kingdom is ſet up, and a worldlike power maintained, who ſerves by the brain for worldlike gain.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="letter">
               <head>
                  <hi>Epiſt. II.</hi> Concerning our Reſtitution, Captivity, San<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctification, Aſcenſion and <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nion.</head>
               <p>BEginning with that in <hi>Eph.</hi> 1.9, 10. <hi>That in the diſpenſation of the fulneſs of time, he might gather together in one all things in Chriſt, both which are in heaven and which are on earth, even in him.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>There is a time for all purpoſes that are decreed by the Father, to be fulfilled in their times and ſeaſons; a day for to fall, a
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:170026:6"/>day to reign as Kings, one hour with the Beaſt in his fall, a day for to be ſenſible of his fall: a day to be ſenfible of the terrors and puniſhments by his fall, and a day to be ſenſible of his loſs of Gods preſence and communion with him, and a day to a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bide the trial of the fire, which ſhall ſearch the heart, and try the reins of man: a day for all fleſhly glory to fall before the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence of the Lord: a day to mourn for theſe changes: a day for to go through the fiery trial, and to be refined again: and again, a day to behold the manifeſtation of God to be like Flames of Fire, to kin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dle every where, where it cometh; then ſhall the <hi>ſmoaking flax</hi> be ſet on fire, then will the Lord ſay unto the Sons of men, <hi>Ariſe and ſhine, for your light is come;</hi> then ſhall you ariſe from the dead, and Chriſt ſhal give you life, then am I come ſaith he, that you may have life, and that you may have it more abundantly, and you who were abſent from me, ſhal return to your fathers houſe, like the prodigal, and be pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent with me where I am. And then you that ſeed upon husks, and were wanderers and ſtrangers to the <hi>Land of Promiſe,</hi> the <hi>Land of the Living,</hi> thus being refined, Chriſt wil preſent you unblameable and
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:170026:7"/>unrebukable, without ſpot or blemiſh be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the Throne of <hi>God,</hi> and you ſhall bee unto him a ſweet ſavor, a ſaerifice which he is well pleaſed with; then ſaith he, Come my own delight, come my own children, which are neer and dear unto mee, who iſſued out of my own bowels, which my womb brought forth, to the glory and praiſe of my own name, even ſo ſhall it be by my gathering thoſe that are afar off, and thoſe that are nigh, into my glory, then is the time come, that the Father wil glorifie us, that we may glorifie him, then ſhal we know the time that the Lord doth gather in his ſewels, which ſhal ſhine moſt glori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ously in their Cabinets, then ſhal they who have the ſingle eye, behold and ſee that Chriſt is come the ſecond time without ſin unto ſalvation, <hi>Heb.</hi> 9.28. Therefore <hi>Lift up your heads, O ye gates, even lift them up, ye everlaſting doors, and the King of glory ſhal come in,</hi> Pſalm 24.9. Conſider, that Chriſt is the head of every Saint, and to be a Saint is to be ſanctified and drawn up into union with Chriſt; <hi>for he that ſan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctifieth, and they that are ſanctified are all of one,</hi> Heb. 2.11. which makes them gates to ſhew forth his praiſe, and to exalt their head, then ſhal we know, that he that de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcended
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:170026:7"/>is the ſame alſo that aſoended, and know this, that there is a deſcending, before there is an aſcending, and that which doth deſcend muſt alſo aſcend, ſo every thing ſhal return into its Centre, if you are ſpiritual you muſt aſcend into the internal Court, and the heavens ſhal bee bowed down at the preſence of the Lord, for the riſing up of all Saints into union with him, when the day of remptation is upon all the world; for there is no approach, no converſe, no ſweet intercourſe between <hi>God</hi> and the <hi>Creature,</hi> but in him, by him, and through him; and this conſider, if you are not riſen with Chriſt, ye are dead, and your life is hid with <hi>Chriſt</hi> in <hi>God,</hi> and theſe things are hid from your eyes and preſent enjoyment likewiſe; therefore let every one examine his own heart, and conſider what an eſtate he is in, whether it bee in darkneſs or in light, or whether the day of the Lord hath been upon thee, that thou art changed thereby from death to life, and ſo from glory to glory, and to be gathered out of all things below <hi>God</hi> whatſoever, that thou canſt truly ſay, that <hi>Chriſt</hi> who is our life, has appeared, &amp; we appear with him in glory, then thou art able to dwel wth conſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming fire, &amp; to live in diſpenſations, &amp;a life a
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:170026:8"/>to appear where the Lord appears, and not to ſmite at thy poor brethren, who Chriſt died for.</p>
               <p>This conſider, That all Nations are made of one blood, and have all life and breath by one <hi>God, Act.</hi> 7.26. yet this great lump being brought forth, though they are all the ſame, all of one blood, yet they are cut out into two parcels, <hi>Jews</hi> and <hi>Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiles,</hi> and they are as diſtinct as may be, both in their <hi>ways,</hi> and in their <hi>God,</hi> in their <hi>Laws, Ordinances, deſires, ends</hi> and <hi>hopes;</hi> the <hi>Jews</hi> muſt not be like the <hi>Gentiles</hi> in a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny thing, the <hi>Gentiles</hi> will not be like the <hi>Jews</hi> in any thing; Oh how diverſe and diſtinct, and contrary are they! but this diſtinction muſt not always laſt, for when Chriſt comes forth to give up that princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple of life in himſelf, and to slay it in them, whereby they have thus lived, the leaves and fruit of variety and diſtinction wil ſoon wither, and they will all return back into union and harmony again, then ſhall the earth diſeloſe her blood, ſo Chriſt brings them both into one, and takes them both, with all their differences, into his own Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy, and deſtroys all their differences, and offers up all that God dislikes in them, in his own Body on the Croſs, and ſo ſweetly
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:170026:8"/>heals up the differences between God and the Creatures by his intire love unto them.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="letter">
               <head>
                  <hi>Epiſt. III.</hi> Concerning ſeven diſpenſations, which hath, and ſhall be fulfilled in their end of time.</head>
               <p>THe firſt diſpenſation was, when God gave the Law to <hi>Adam</hi> as ſoon as he had made him, as, <hi>In the day thou eateſt, thou ſhalt die.</hi> Now this Law it was holy, juſt, and good, yet it was a killing word, (or the killing letter) for it took hold on <hi>Adams</hi> diſobedience, and slew him, ſo all Fleſh died, for all Fleſh broke the Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant in <hi>Adam,</hi> and ſo all Humane Fleſh was caſt under that diſpenſation of death; ſo every oppoſite eſtate wil ſeek to advance it ſelf.</p>
               <p>The ſecond diſpenſation, is in the firſt Promiſe, or Manifeſtation of the Love of God to the creature, and the Curſe to the Serpent, in theſe words, <hi>The ſeed of the woman ſhall bruiſe the Scrpents head,</hi> Gen. 3.15. &amp; 22.18. and this continued from <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dam</hi> til <hi>Abraham.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="12" facs="tcp:170026:9"/>
Then the third diſpenſation or diſcovery of God is more clear, than the former, for unto <hi>Abraham</hi> he ſpeaks more particularly, he doth not ſtil ſay in general terms, the ſeed of the woman,—but in thy ſeed <hi>Abra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham</hi> (all Nations of the earth) ſhal bee bleſſed, and ſo points out more directly in what lineage and generation of Mankinde, God would firſt appear in, to bruiſe the Serpents head, and this diſpenſation con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinued from <hi>Abraham</hi> to <hi>Moſes,</hi> and they imbraced the promiſes.</p>
               <p>The fourth diſpenſation is from <hi>Moſes</hi> till God manifeſted himſelf in the Fleſh, or till Jeſus Chriſt was born of <hi>Mary,</hi> who was one of the houſe of <hi>David,</hi> and of the lineage of <hi>Abraham,</hi> and this diſpenſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion is more clear than the former, for God by Types, and Figures, and Ceremonies and Shadows, did manifeſt his love to his creatures, and his wrath to the Serpent, as we may underſtand, when God appears in <hi>Johns</hi> Baptiſm, or the Water Baptiſm, which did much type forth the Baptiſm of the Spirit by Fire and the Holy Ghoſt, which ſhould refine and purifie them, and ſaith <hi>John</hi> I muſt decreaſe (or that adminiſtration I lived in) but he that cometh after me, which is Chriſt, ſhal increaſe, and ſhal
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:170026:9"/>baptize you with the Holy Ghoſt, and alſo God did manifeſtly ſet forth his love by the Prophets in that diſpenſation, for then was the ſhadow of the Law of <hi>Moſes</hi> falling, and <hi>Goſpel-Truths</hi> riſing, whereby they ſhould be the more ceaſing from Man, whoſe breath is in his Noſtrils; and ſo like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe the love of <hi>God</hi> did much appear when the ſacrifice was ſlain and offered, then <hi>God</hi> received an atonement, it being a type of <hi>Gods</hi> in-dwelling in the Fleſh, or a ſhadow of Chriſt the Lamb, the ſubſtances of all thoſe <hi>ſacrifices,</hi>—and I pray you conſider thoſe things which are ſpoken allegorically concerning <hi>Achan, Joſh.</hi> 7.26. where it ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pears, that when <hi>Achan</hi> that troubled <hi>Iſrael</hi> was put to death in the valley of <hi>Achor,</hi> the fierceneſs of <hi>Gods</hi> wrath was turned away. And in <hi>Hoſea,</hi> ch: 2. v: 14, 15. where he ſaith, <hi>I wil give the valley of A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cher for a door of hope,</hi> which was the place of <hi>Achans</hi> death; ſo when the Serpent who is our trouble, is ſubdued and killed in the valley of <hi>human fleſh,</hi> then the diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penſation of mods anger is turned away.</p>
               <p>The fifth diſpenſation, is from the time that God was manifeſted in the fleſh, in the perſon of Ieſus Chriſt, to the time that he appeared in the fleſh and perſon of his
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:170026:10"/>Saints; likewiſe this alſo is more clear then the former, for Ieſus the annoynted, was the ſubſtance of all thoſe types and ſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dows of the Moſaical Law, for now God doth manifeſtly appear to dwel in the fleſh, and by a manifeſt being, to ſet the Creature free from bonbage, and by Immortal life to ſwallow mort I beings into himſelf.</p>
               <p>The ſixth diſpenſation is from the time that God appeared in the fleſh of the Saints, till the perfect gathering up of <hi>the Elect,</hi> which is the work of that diſpenſati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on —which is called a Referrection day, or a great day of Iudgment, for ſo long as the Iudge ſits upon the Iudgment ſeat it is the day of Iudgment, which he doth in every diſpenſation, until the time of the Reſtitution of all things, both which are in heaven and which are on earth, even in Chriſt, <hi>Eph.</hi> 1.10. <hi>Rev</hi> 10.7. but in the dayes of the voice of the ſeventh Angel, when he ſhal begin to ſound, the myſtery of God ſhould be finiſhed, as he hath de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clared to his ſervants the Prophets, ſo <hi>Gor. i.</hi> 15.24. then cometh the end when he that is Chriſt ſhal have delivered up his Kingdom to God even the Father, com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pared with <hi>Acts</hi> 3.21: — and this alſo is more clear then the former, as God appear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:170026:10"/>in Chriſt who is the root of the creation, it was a ſign of God the father appearing in the whole body; for ſaith Chriſt, I and the children that thou haſt gave me for ſignes and wonders: and according to his promiſe by <hi>Joel,</hi> ch. 2. v. 28. I wil powre out my ſpirit upon all Fleſh, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> the Apoſtles alſo finding the ſame in them ſelves, bare witneſs to it, <hi>Acts</hi> 2.16.</p>
               <p>And thus I give you a hint of the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venth diſpenſation, when the Goſpels de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claration ſhall be fulfilled, and we to be transformed and changed into the Heaven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Image whereby all things may be reſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red into the Indiſſolable band, into the u<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity and peace of God which paſseth all underſtanding of man, and all wars to ceaſe; for ſo long as diſpenſations laſt and we under them, we are at warts among our ſelves, and with God alſo in one ſenſe, and a rechangable while we are under diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penſations, and are to be changed from glory to glory, &amp; as God doth in Scripture declare ſeven great diſpenſations, or diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>coveries of his counſel and will; each one clearer then other, yet in every one of theſe, God doth ſend forth ſeveral other diſpenſations by the hand of Angels, for the carrying on of the work, of that time
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:170026:11"/>and ſeaſon, which are diſcoveries of his glory, for whatſoever comes from God is a ſpiritual power, and it may be ſaid to be declared by angels, as when God ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peared in diſcoveries to his peopel, an angel is ſaid to appear unto them, as to <hi>Joſeph</hi> in a dream, <hi>Zachariah</hi> in a viſion; unto <hi>Araham</hi> and <hi>Lot</hi> it is ſaid Angels appear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, and likewiſe he ſhall ſend his angels with a great ſound of a trumpet, and they ſhall gather together his Elect from four winds, from one end of heaven to the other, <hi>Math.</hi> 24.30, 31. then ſhall all the holy ſeed be gathered in, and appear in its glory, then the tribes of the earth ſhal mourn, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe of the deſolation of their Kingdom, —then I. is taken, and I. is left.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="letter">
               <head>
                  <hi>Epiſt. IV.</hi> A diſcovery of the Reign of the Beaſt of Baby<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lons City, which hath made the nations drunk with wine of her fornication.</head>
               <p>I Shall begid with that of <hi>Daniel,</hi> ch. 8. v. 23.24, 25. and in the later time of their Kingdome, when the tranſgreſſors
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:170026:11"/>are come to the full, a King of fierce coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenance, and underſtanding, dark ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tences, and his power ſhal be mighty, but not by his own power, and he ſhal deſtroy wonderfully, and ſhal proſper and practiſe, and ſhall deſtroy the mighty, and the holy people, and through his policy alſo, he ſhal cauſe craft to proſper in his hand, and he ſhal magnifie himſelf in his heart, and by peace ſhal deſtroy many, he ſhal alſo ſtand up againſt the Prince of Princes, but he ſhal be broken down with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out hand.</p>
               <p>And all this time, that God is gathering together <hi>the Elect</hi>—he hath given a time, times and half a time, to the Serpent, which in theſe threefold ſhapes and a half, or in theſe three days and a half, he is called the Beaſt Ruling in the Whore, and this time is given him to make war, and to fight againſt the Prince of Princes and his Saints, and to overcome then, and to waſte and deſtroy the holy People mightily, and this appointed time, is the year or ſeaſon wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in the Beaſt lives, and God gives all advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tages to the Beaſt, as riches, ontward liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty,—worldy power, and generally human authority into his hand, whereby he reigns, and is the Idol. God of this world—and
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:170026:12"/>hath put no weapons into the hands of the Saints,—but the anoynting and ſword of the Spirit of the Lord, to fight againſt the reproaches, ſlanders, opprſſions, poverties, weaknſſe, wickedneſſe, Priſons, and the multitude of temptations, which the Beaſt through her wit, malice, police, and pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er, doth caſt upon the Saints, like a flood of water to drowne, and deſtroy, and over come the worke of God, in his coming forth in the Spirit,—if it were poſſible, — likewiſe, the Serpent ſtirs up ſome whom he diſcerns to be ſeeming profeſſors, outwardly religious, having a form of Godlineſſe, but through hypocriſie, pride, and ſelfiſhneſs, deny the power, and diſho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nor God, and diſcourage the tender Lambs of Chriſt, and caſt an ill reproach upon the wayes of God; and hence it is, that <hi>Iſarel</hi> of old were trampled upon—by the <hi>Gentiles</hi> in the Fleſh that were not in Covenant with them, but were under the condemning law, who have trod under foot the blood of the new covenant, and hence it is, that the Beaſt muſt tread the holy City underfoot two &amp; forty months, which ſignifieth his Reign is but for a ſhort ſpace of time, but now in theſe latter dayes, when the time, times and half, drawe
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:170026:12"/>to an end—then God ſends forth ſeveral diſpenſations, and Angels, aſſiſting to the ſixth and great diſpenſation, wherein the Lords appearance wil blaſt all the glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry of the Beaſt, and Immaginary part of man; therefore ye that adorn your ſelves with <hi>Babylons</hi> painting, fair outſides of ſeveral colors, and dreſſes of <hi>Edoms</hi> die, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold the Lord is coming to execute Iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment upon his adverſaries and our oppreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſors, and to poure out Vials of wrath upon all the glory of the Beaſt, and to ſtain the pride of all fleſh, whereby he curſes all their glory by ſeaven degrees, by the voice of God, through Angels and Saints, ſoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding forth ſeaven Trumpets of glory to God one after another, which is perfection of glory to the Saints, or Church of the firſt borne,—which implies perfection, of ruin upon every particular of the Beaſt, blaſting, curſing or the downefall of their Kingdom,—Oh! that all profeſſors had a zeal of God according to knoledg, that they may not be like the wilde ſigrree that Chriſt curſed, which was ſul of leaves, but no fruit, for iniquity abounds, and the love of many, in whom the Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pent rules, waxeth cold, and extreme' bit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, and mad againſt the Saints, in whom
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:170026:13"/>the anoynted rules, ſo that they gnaſh their tongues with vexation of ſpirit, and the ſmoak of their torment aſcends upward, and ſo they have no reſt day nor night, who worſhip the Beaſt and his Image, and whoſoever receiveth the <hi>Mark</hi> of his <hi>Name;</hi> and thus conſider, while God ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fers the Beaſt co Reign, it is called the day of the Beaſt, and God hath given him three dayes and a half, to tread the holy City underfoot, or the ſpace of two and forty months, which is three ſhapes, three diſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veries of the Reign of the Beaſt, or three degrees and a half, of the Serpents Refor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation, from bad to worſe, from open pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phaneneſs, to cloſe hypocriſie; <hi>Rev.</hi> 17.4. therefore let error, ſin, devil and darkneſſe come forth in their power, it is the wil of God they ſhould do ſo, that it may appear to be more then what it is,—and that old <hi>Herode</hi> may be diſcovered which ſeeketh the life of the childe Ieſus as ſoon as he is borne of any Virgin Spirit; alſo that <hi>Pha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raoh</hi> should riſe unto his ful greatneſſe,—that God may appear to be above, and to get himſelf honor upon him, for he wil be glorified by both, veſſels of honor and veſſels of dishonor; Antichriſt is now get<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting up upon his laſt leggs, whoſe leggs are
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:170026:13"/>Iron, and feet clay: there is life no where but in his ſtump, which often has been lap't, but yet the root remaines alive which is not enough to quicken—through<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly in this his laſt Image and form in which he is coming forth like unto an Angel of light; but how ſoon was he thrown down in his laſt appearance and riſing among us? even before he could bite, his teeth were broken; god ſmote him on the cheek-bone, before the thorns were growne hard to prick, the fire took hold of them, which fire is kindling the ſmoak ſparkles, to burn downe the tall Cedars, and God is finiſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the work apace and cutting it short in righteouſneſſe, even to the utter conſump<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion and deſtruction of his enemies by the brightneſſe of his coming; <hi>Jacob</hi> shall be a Fire, and <hi>Eſau</hi> for ſtubble, God wil be a ſwift witneſſe againſt this Sorcery, for ſo are all the dealings of natural men in things of god, and by terrible things wil he anſwer them: and this conſider, that the foundation that ſome profeſſors are laying, in ſeveral wayes or opinions shutted to their eyes, which wil appear to be the a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bomination of deſolation ſpoken of by <hi>Danel</hi> the prophet, all the riſing and puttings forth of Antichriſt are faire and
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:170026:14"/>wel looking, but God doth pronounce the final Curſe againſt it, which was a fruit that ſprung up in the created being, and acted both inwardly and outwardly, but Gods deſign is to weed out the tares from the good of the corn, but the husbandmen think that by this husbandry, the wheat wil be pulled up with the tares, nay they think the wheat wil be deſtroyed, and the tares nouriſhed, becauſe they are unskilful of the work, but the Lord is now reſolved that the wheat ſhal ſpread and flouriſh, and he wil come and ſever the tares from the wheat, and throw out thoſe husbandmen with them into the Fire, which beat his Servants and would have killed the Heir, therefore their vineyard ſhal be taken away and given to another people,—therefore let all Fleſh be ſilent before the Lord, for he is raiſed up to make known his power for the proclaiming of <hi>Iſraels</hi> return, and the captivity of his people, <hi>Zach.</hi> 2.13. for the Lord wil build her again that hath been trodden down, and plant her in the mag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nificents beauty of beauties, in royal and adorative glory: O my beloved! my ſoul is raviſhed with the delightful delight, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firing you may be gathered into union in the celeſtial centre, in the boſom of the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="5" type="letter">
               <pb n="23" facs="tcp:170026:14"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>Epiſt: V.</hi> Concerning a further diſcovery of Antichriſt in man, and of the Spirit of God in man, diſcovering that Antichriſt what he is, and where he rules.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>ANd every ſpirit that confeſſeth not, that Jeſus Chriſt is come in the fleſh, is not of God; and this is that ſpirit of Antichriſt, whereof you have heard that it ſhould come, and even now already is in the world,</hi> 1 Ioh. 4.3.</p>
               <p>Who hath known the minde of God? the ſpiritual man, that cannot but confeſs, that Chriſt is come in the Fleſh, by his u<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion that he hath with him in the ſpirit, and is enlightened by the Reſurrection from the dead, whereby his works declare him that they are of the Father, not onely in word, but in power and demonſtration of the Spirit, whereby they abound in all goodneſs; for <hi>ſo are the fruits of the Spirit, as love, joy, peace, long-ſuffering, gentleneſs, goodneſs, faith, meekneſs, temperance, againſt ſuch there is no Law,</hi> Gal. 5.23.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="24" facs="tcp:170026:15"/>
Now who are they that confeſſeth not that Chriſt is come in the Fleſh? even they in whom the Spirit of Antichrft rules and is predominate in them, whereby they bring forth the fruits of wickedneſſe by their own Beaſtial reaſon; now who is an Antichriſt? even he that denieth the Father and the Son, 1. <hi>John.</hi> 2, 22. and all that obey not the command of Chriſt, which doth bring us unto God; then Antichriſt muſt be the unbeleeving Spirit, that cannot con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſe Chriſt by the fruits of the Spirit of God, and by his mercies held forth in le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus Chriſt unto him in his creaturely eſtate: this know, whileſt thou art in this dark, ignorant, polluted, defild, eſtate, thou haſt an Antichriſt Devil, falſe Prophet within thee, as it doth appear by <hi>Peter,</hi> when Chriſt ſaid unto him, <hi>Got the dehinde mee Satan, for thou ſavoreſt not the things of God, but of man;</hi> then look no more for Anti-Chriſt abroad or at <hi>Rome,</hi> but at home, and do not thruſt it off from one unto another, and one country unto another Nation, when indeed it is Antichriſt his trade to keep our eyes without, leſt we ſhould ſee his deceit within; Antichriſt is alſo the whore that holds forth ber Golden Cup ful of abomination and filthineſſe of her
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:170026:15"/>fornication, <hi>Rev.</hi> 17.4, which deceives the nations and wipes her mouth, and ſaid I have done no wrong, when ſhee hath acted what ſhee can; therefore tremble, tremble, tremble, for the day of the Lord wil renounce the hidden things of diſho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſty, and the ſecrets of your hearts ſhal be laid open, and you ſhal be as ſtubble for the Fire in that day, then ſhal he ſhake every ſtrong hold, and your fortified places, and your high towers; yea, he wil ſhake both heaven and earth, both inwardly and outwardly, ſo that there wil be no ſafety no where but in the Lord, for he ſhal bee the hiding place, until the indignation of the Lord be overpaſt, that thoſe things which cannot be ſhaken (being himſelf) may remain, when he ſhal turn upſide down, and overturn all things that are not according to truth, and ſtrength, and know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledg, wiſdom and power of Chriſt Jeſus; therefore weight diligently upon the Lord, that hou maiſt be found in him, not having thine own righteouſnes, but the righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes of Chriſt, even the Lord our righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes; therfore behold there is a wild Figtree, that was a ſhow of a goodly good tree afar off to dark eys, but to com cloſe to the Fig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tree, &amp; you my brethren after the fleſh, wch vaunt your ſelvs in human learning &amp; brain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wit,
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:170026:16"/>then like the Fgtree are ye, and are ful of beautious leaves (without) of expreſſions, but to come to the fruit, ye are carnal, and devilliſh in action; by the fruit ye ſhal know them, if you are able to diſtinguiſh of fruits, by the Spirit of God, which ſhal try the ſpirits and the works of man of what ſort they are: Now there is but light and darkneſs in which man worketh in, either light or darkneſs, and this is the definition, God is light, and that light is love; now Man in that love is in light, and that onely light is Chriſt; now as God is light, the Devil is but darkneſs to that light, now in darkneſs is hatred, malice, envy, covetouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, and the root of all bitterneſs, which is the Devil; therefore you that would be holy, depart from theſe evils, for it is the highway of the righteous to depart from iniquity.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="6" type="letter">
               <pb n="27" facs="tcp:170026:16"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>Epiſt. VI.</hi> Of an heavenly eſtate of things in the new <hi>Ieruſalem,</hi> in man, and of the death of the Creature in an eſtate below God.</head>
               <p>TO come cloſe to the matter: In a word, it is this hel is called death, or a conditon below life, and this is twofold, either a death far below the nature of God, or a death of ſorrows, which is a condition far below the comforts and en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyments of God; now every man and woman as they are branches of <hi>Adam</hi> in the fall, they have no purity in themſelves, and therefore in a hel far below the life and nature of God, and likewiſe they are unavoydably ſubject to the ſorrows of that death, and have no power to deliver them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves out of that bondage, for God is on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly our Redeemer and Deliverer, therefore he ſent his Son not to condemn the world, but that the world through him might be ſaved, <hi>Joh.</hi> 3.17. Therefore it followeth clear, that if men were capable of ſo much mercy, being Gods creatures, as to be deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vered
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:170026:17"/>from the guilt of Sin and of Death, which is one part of Hel, or a condition below life eternal, then wil they be capable to be delivered through the mercy of the ſame God, from the ſorrowes and pains that followeth ſin, both which God in his time wil deliver his Creation from,</p>
               <p>Secondly, the heavenly eſtate is to live unto God with the life of Chriſt in the knowledg thereof of his power; and to know God to be his all in all,—to love his Enemies, to do good to them that hate you, and perſecute you, to be all in love, to injoy God in time of trouble, or at all times, and to be with him in Spirit where he is; this is an Heavenly eſtate, to ſee the inviſible appear in the viſible, and to ſwal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low it up in it ſelf, in love—as <hi>Enech</hi> that walked with God and was not, but there is ſuch a way for Saints to go, before they come to injoy their Kingdome, or to enter into their glory, as followeth, as Ieſus Chriſt hath ſhewed us, in that which is called the Lords Supper and Baptiſm, that no Fleſh wil indure it, as wil appear, Firſt, from thoſe words of Chriſt in <hi>Mat.</hi> 20.19.20.21. for when he was defired by the mother of <hi>Zebedees</hi> children, that her two ſons might ſit the one at his right hand
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:170026:17"/>and the other at his left, in his kingdome, his anſwer was, <hi>You know not what you ask; for,</hi> ſaith he, <hi>Are ye able to drink of the Cup that</hi> I <hi>ſhal drink of, and to be Baptiſed with the Baptiſme what Jam Baptiſed withall?</hi> As if he ſhould ſay, the way that leads to my kindome, is a Crucifying way, even from the beginning, to the end, as it was with me, who was perſecuted, from my birth to my death: it is a way ſprinkled with blood, and burning with Fire, very ſharp and bitter, and no ſweetneſſe in it; for many ſtorms and tempeſts wil ariſe and fall upon your travel to <hi>Canaan,</hi> you muſt be crowned with thorts, and you muſt be tempted with the Serpent, buffeted with Satan, and perſecuted with <hi>Herod,</hi> and how are you able to endure this? ſaith they, <hi>we are</hi> able; then ſaith Chriſt again, <hi>you ſtall indeed drink of the Cup that J drink of, and be baptiſed with the baptiſme that J am baptiſed with, but to ſit on my right hand, and on my left is not mine to give, but it ſhall be given to chem for whom it is prepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red of my Father:</hi> which is as much as to ſay, you muſt ſuffer the loſſe of all things below, or beſides me, and the way which I have gone you ſhall go, the death which I have ſuffered, you ſhall in ſome meaſure
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:170026:18"/>ſuffer, and then having gon the way, and ſuffered the death, you wil ſay, <hi>Father Glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rifie thy Son, that thy Son may Glorifie thee,</hi> then wil he give you a crown of life, which is laid up for you in the kingdom of hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven, and as <hi>Paul</hi> ſaith, <hi>J have run the race, and obtained the price in Jeſus Chriſt, J have finiſhed my croſs, henceforth is laid up for me a Crown of glory, even</hi> the Lord; and Chriſt himſelf ſaith, <hi>that for the glory which was ſet before him, he indured the croſſe, and deſpiſed the ſhame, drunk his cup and received his Baptiſme, and after entred into his glory:</hi> And thus he went before us as a pattern, or an example for us, but when we have ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained the Kingdom, and received the Crown, the kingdom being delivered up to the father, we are not,—Chriſt is all,—unto God the onely one, for we then are not our owne, but we are Chriſts, and Chriſt is Gods, and ſo an union betwixt Chriſt and us, and an union betwixt God and Chriſt into one,—entire and alone eſſence, then is the Kingdome deliverd up unto God by Chriſt, and then God the Father is as he was, that is, all in all—and out of that all—all came forth,—and into that all—ſhall all be through Chriſt, (who is the ſtrength of God) be reduced
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:170026:18"/>into God, and yet a viſible appearance — through the inviſible, and in him to appe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ar; this is one glimps of the myſtery of the Divine Deity operative, acting through it ſelf in the illuſtration of it ſelf,—which is wiſdoms work and the Spirits teaching; therefore, <hi>let all fleſh be ſilent before tke Lord, for it is not he that heareth my words,</hi> Saith Chriſt, <hi>but he that doth my will, he it is that is my diſciple, bleſſed for ever in the name of the Father.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="7" type="letter">
               <head>
                  <hi>Epiſt. VII.</hi> Concerning a word of exhortation to Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans to ſupport the bruiſed Reed, that the ſmoaking flax may be ſet on fire in theſe <hi>Goſpel-times.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>O How good a thing it is for Chriſtians to walk cloſe with God in that diſpen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſation wherein he appeareth unto them in; for no one can truly ſerve God out of that diſpenſation wherein he appeareth unto them; therefore then to walk up to what they know, and to judg others that are not under the ſame, though there be ſeveral di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpenſations or adminiſtrations, yet the ſame Lord, though they may be ſeverally acted, yet all by one ſpirit, if they be ſincere and upright in heart, and of a meek and quiet
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:170026:19"/>ſpirit, who dwels in love, otherwiſe they are but the world; a Saint is known by one of the ſame ſpirit, and diſowned by the world, for they love their own, and the proof of a Saint is to ſhow his ſtrength in time of need, that is, to own all things that is of God, and to bear with the weak bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren, and to cheriſh that in them which is to be cheriſhed, and to offer up that to the fire which is to be burnt: But how prone is man to be judging and condemning! Man hath an eye and light in his day, and he cannot forbear paſſing his judgment there upon things or perſons: the natural man wil be judging natural things, and the ſpiritual man wil be judging ſpiritual things, men wil be judging men, Chriſtians wil be judging Chriſtians, yea both wil be judging: there is a day of man, and the day of God, man is judging in his day, if there be not ſo much light as to make the day of the Lord appear in man, it is but mans day and ſo the worthleſneſs of his judgment appears in <hi>Pauls</hi> account <hi>for</hi> ſaith he, <hi>it is with me avery ſmall thing that I ſhould be judged of you, or of mans judgment; man cannot be more forward to judg me, then I am to ſlight him in that ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion,</hi> for mans judgment is too ſhallow to judg in ſpiritual things: <hi>judg not</hi> (ſaith Chriſt) and he himſelf forbear judging: <hi>I
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:170026:19"/>judg no man,</hi> Iob 8, 15. though if he had judged, his judgment had been true, verſ. 16. yet being not his time to judg, though he was judg, he could for bear his ſentence, until the proper ſeaſon of it, therfore ſaith <hi>Paul, judg nothing before the time, until the Lord come, who wil both bring to light the hid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den things of darkueſs, and wil make mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſt the counſels of the heart,</hi> therefore, ſaith <hi>Paul, With me it is a very ſmall thing that J ſhould be judged of you or of mans judgment, yea I judg not mine own ſelf,</hi> 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 4.3. Who art thou that indgeſt another mans ſervant to his own maſter? he ſtandeth or falleth: or wherein thou iudgeſt another, thou condemneſt thy ſelf, it belongs to the Lord to be iudg, for thou, O man, haſt no more right to iudg thy fellow ſervant, then he has to iudg thee: therfore iudg nothing be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the time in the things of God, for he has kept his own light for his own day, which ſhall lay open the ſecrets of every mans heat: therefore he that is under one diſcovery, let him not iudg another that is under another diſcovery, and let not them who ſerve God in diſpenſations, iudg them in whom he wil be ſerved above diſpenſati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, and ſo to limit and confine God how or where he ſhall appear, or be ſerved: but
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:170026:20"/>as <hi>every one hath received of the gift of God, ſo let them miniſter the ſame as good ſtewards of his manifold grace,</hi> 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 4.10. therfore note it is a gift which cannot be purchaſed by mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny as human learning is, which ſervs but for external things, and cannot look into the internal, as can the gift which is given, even the ſpirit of truth, which needeth not to be ſupported by human learning, for it is ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ported by he that gives; but human lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning is made a cloak to cover ignorance and hypocrifie, and to deceive the ſimple, but when it is grown to the ful heighth, it ſhal fal, and then great Babylon ſhal fal, and her mourners ſhal be many: Therefore I pray you ſet no greater a price of it, then what it is worth, for when God called for Preach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers he called Fiſhermen, as was <hi>Peter,</hi> and Shepheards as was <hi>Moſes</hi> and <hi>David,</hi> and Herdſmen, as <hi>Amos,</hi> and <hi>Eliſha</hi> a Plowman, Chriſt himſelf was call'd a Carpenter, <hi>Paul</hi> a Tentmaker, but he could ſpeak Tongues be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing brought up at the feet of <hi>Gamaliel:</hi> but for althat, he was a perſecutor of the church before his converſion, therefore let not one ſort of people have any preiudice againſt a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nother, for God wil cal whom he pleaſeth, and wil be honored where he pleaſeth, and can take of al ſorts ſom to manifeſt his glory;
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:170026:20"/>therfore be waiting upon God, and ceaſing from man, whoſe breath is in his noſtrils, &amp; ſo fulfil the commands of Chriſt, ſee that you love one another, love al men, even your enemies, do good to them that hate you, &amp; the God of love wil cover you when the ſtorme shal fal upon the wicked: O beloved! did you but know how lovely you are be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in love, for love ſheweth the deformity in all that is not in love,—but it is not ſeen but by loves own eye, what an oneneſs there is in your ſelves being in love, &amp; what an oneneſs in multiplicities being in love, which wil ſet the ſmoaking Flax on a bright Flame, &amp; wil kindle every little ſpark where it comes; Love is that which ties all the Bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren in a knot, God is love, and he that dwelleth in that love dwelleth in God, and God in him; <hi>Herein is our love made perfect, that we may have boldneſs in the day of Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, becauſe as he is, ſo are we in this world.</hi> 1 Joh. 4.16.17.</p>
               <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="poem">
            <l>If you our land would know wherin we overflow,</l>
            <l>It is <hi>Canaan</hi> wherin the pleaſant plants do grow.</l>
            <l>Which from the root they yeeld their fruit now</l>
            <l>Of heavenly glory forth to ſhow:</l>
            <l>Not in notion, but our portion, which ſatisfits us</l>
            <l>Yea, the Sun which is ſo tranſparent bright</l>
            <l>With its ſarafic al light,</l>
            <l>Power ſtrength and might;</l>
            <pb n="36" facs="tcp:170026:21"/>
            <l>Which turns all the beholders into its right,</l>
            <l>And puts an end to war and ſtrife,</l>
            <l>Which in Religions fight.</l>
            <l>But in darkneſs, not in light,</l>
            <l>Wherein their actions attend to ſtrife,</l>
            <l>Which fruit doth ſhow where it doth grow,</l>
            <l>In human nature far below,</l>
            <l>Which is a Hell to the creatures woe</l>
            <l>When the vials come where that doth grow:</l>
            <l>Which ſhal ſcorch and blaſt</l>
            <l>That which man doth hold ſo faſt:</l>
            <l>Then mans teaching that ſhal fal,</l>
            <l>Which hath long time ſtood like a wal,</l>
            <l>Then <hi>Melchiſedec</hi> a Preacher unto us ſhal be, partition wal,</l>
            <l>Jn perfect unitie.</l>
            <l>So <hi>God</hi> who is our all, by breaking down the</l>
            <l>Wil deliver <hi>Iſrael</hi> all from bondage and from thral.</l>
            <l>So ſhal the light which is ſo bright,</l>
            <l>Shine both far and neer,</l>
            <l>Then perfect love ſhal caſt out fear,</l>
            <l>That we in heaven may appear</l>
            <l>With our glory in the Sphere,</l>
            <l>Then for to be what at firſt we were,</l>
            <l>Before in Creation we did appear,</l>
            <l>That Chriſt in one may all then be,</l>
            <l>
               <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nto eternity.</l>
            <l>Then the pathment of our <hi>God</hi> in glory bright,</l>
            <l>Always a day, there is no night.</l>
            <l>From that Imperial Throne</l>
            <l>Declares the glory of union.</l>
            <trailer>Finis.</trailer>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
